all right we are live well to project
raising for culture creation
Thank You Richie and Kylie for joining
us you'd realize like always here do you
want to give us a brief rundown Richie
of what culture creation is or if I said
it wrong the actual name of it and then
what you're out of Road
yeah sure I'm so this culture create it
and yeah it's just a small project of
mine the idea is to get a group of
people together and see if we can refine
a culture together that is directed more
at building stronger bonds taking care
of one another more effectively becoming
[Music]
more of fictive it is a great just you
know it's it's pretty broad in terms of
the things that I'm hoping to achieve
with it which means it's going to be
quite difficult to really communicate to
the people went to other people you know
what the scope is but my hope is that we
can find a few that make the project
kind of self-sustaining I'd like it to
be really goal orientated so that we're
always doing something new and we're
learning new skills and developing
anything personal growth yeah that's
kind of it all right for those the
aspirations in there that's part of it
you yeah yeah my pen wasn't working so I
didn't really and I can't read my
writing now but to find a way to make it
self-sustaining and you want to remain
cool oriented I believe when I read the
paper you had written it's very like
personal development meets actual like a
project but not a long-term project more
of like a
project or I'm something that you can
get right away is that crap yeah yeah
well well what I'm hoping to have what
the different projects
over the span of time so at the moment
in the document that's up there I've
divided decisions to the the
conversation side so that's what we do
like a medic group meditation we can
come up with a an ecology of practices
that we can you know do together and
then do some sense making to learn to
really communicate with one another and
build some some overlapping semantic
mapping and then the second week or you
know we've we've spaced it out is sends
it around going out and doing something
so we might go and clean like a river
like clear rubbish or we might learn a
skill maybe there's someone in the group
who's got a skill that they could teach
the group and part of part of the point
of that is that we have this rolling
leadership ethos about it so rather than
any one person being the leader or like
the core organizer or something like
that everyone takes the turn at
developing those skills and have
responsibility so that they can you know
if it's if there's a thing that comes up
and we need to organize then the most
competent person in that domain can step
up and take the leadership and then you
know lead the group and yeah yeah so
yeah so I yeah I guess part of the
challenge will be figuring out what has
group we can go out and go there are a
couple of ideas but yeah but it's yeah
they've been the balance between finding
things that are useful and finding
things that are fondant injuries it's
there so where are you in this process
do you have a group and you're looking
for things to do or you're looking to
start the group or you want things to do
before you recruit the group
so I have a small group that we haven't
started practicing yet I have one of the
people in the group who I'm gonna have a
conversation with sometimes so and just
to lay out all of the details and get
her thoughts on them
I initially spoke to her a while ago
just saying that I was concerned about
you know the trajectory of things and I
was like we need to come up with some
kind of solution so that we can you know
whether the future better and she said
that she's you know people thinking same
sorts of things so yeah I mean because I
have a lot of ideas but it also depends
on what other people are interested in
yeah but yeah in any kind of feedback
any kind of thought could be would be
good I know it's I can figure out we can
brainstorm we can do both really but
like brainstorm how you find those
people or we can also brainstorm some of
those activities that are both useful
and enjoyable to do or ways to kind of
co-create them um or any other thing you
would like us to work on for the project
hmm yeah so so I think in terms of the
the growth of the group I don't think
that'll be too difficult but the key is
really to call it slowly in the
beginning to really yeah get the culture
locked in but activities yeah maybe
brainstorm some ideas about things that
we can actually go out and do it alright
that's good
and you're looking to do these meetings
how often are they every week everybody
yeah so at the moment I'm thinking
weekly but it might be better to the
sort of twice a week
sorry what twice every month and maybe
you want to mop it depends like we'll
have to play around with the potency
just to make sure that it's still
interesting yeah
is it um just four at a project raising
and part of what inspired the project
raising was the idea of a barn raising
right where all of your neighbors come
and help you raise a barn and then when
you need a barn raise theoretically
there to help you would it interest you
to do something like that where you're
actually putting a call out to neighbors
on like what do you need done right a
paint brush fence painted a garden
started and so that's also a way to like
find new people but also to like focus
on one person's project right the issue
is that just like this you might have
more people interested in being the
person having their friends painted the
necessarily painting other offenses but
if depending on who those people are
right if they're seniors if they're
young parents people who really need
that then I think it would feel good to
do it you're not gonna feel like you're
being taken advantage of but does that
resonate with you yeah that's a really
cool idea
yeah because something that is involved
with the communities and something
that's helpful for people because you
know there are a lot of people or just
down on their luck so yeah yeah but
that's a good idea
and also just like a list of because
that's like people can put forward I
need this done or people could also put
it forward hey there's a creek by my
house that really needs cleaning up mmm
maybe they even want to come and help
great create that and you do it's like
that someone had posted and one of the
Facebook users this is our we haven't
been going live on Facebook and YouTube
very often so it's interesting because
it says both well discover Eric and
Richie's faces for a second um that they
go out and say free conversation in
large crowds
and that's a interesting thing of doing
something but my guess is that's not
what you're looking for because we have
a plethora of conversations in our lives
us us us five and yeah going out and
finding more conversation but maybe
other people don't have that and it
might be something that you want to do
Richie what are your personal
circumstances what's it like immediately
around where you live you know where
where do you live what's it like
immediately around you I mean it's a
nice neighborhood lots of forests and
trees and things I bear I'm kind of
still within the city limits
I kind of live like in an apartment
building or any house or in a Kok okay
and like on a street with other houses
kind of thing yeah okay listen I mean I
know this I know this sounds trivial and
mundane but is there anything I mean I
don't know how well you know your
neighbors but is there anything that
needs doing in the immediate environment
a creek that needs cleaning up a pond
that needs putting a bomb that needs
painting you know what I mean you know
something immediate like that you know
in your could just go knock on doors I
mean without this is kind of unnecessary
it seems to me at that level right hmm
yeah I mean yeah that is that is
something that I can do but I think that
the thing that I'm really interested in
is just the the forming those bonds with
a group of people who are interested
initially in the concept because I think
the neighbors either side sort of yeah I
mean I fight I work with my neighbor
over that way but yeah it's just yeah
all these ladies on you is just
something that's been troubling me a lot
Achille recently in trouble it's been
troubling me a lot recently is that you
know we we we try and find a group of
people with whom we share ideas so that
we can explore ideas about how to build
better communities and yet what's right
outside of our front door we don't know
now I know and this is me I mean I'm not
trying to put this on it but this is I
feel this a lot that you know what
what's just you know sorry I'm getting a
little bit tangled up in a thought here
but you wander do you understand what
I'm saying there's a there's an
immediacy in a directness that we seem
to be losing in in all of this talking
about it does that make sense yeah yeah
for sure for sure I mean we've got yoga
Gardens right here so we can we continue
to there yeah sorry correct me if I'm
wrong but you're you're trying to find
groups of people that you can by
alternate have a conversation about what
we're going to do and then go out and do
a thing right and I and I really applaud
that that gap between talking about
doing stuff and actually doing stuff is
is is is is one that we really do need
to really do need to bridge but is it
that's that's basically it right get
together talk about doing something do
the thing then get back together talk
about it how did it go how can we build
on it do the next things that that
basically the idea oh yeah it's
definitely more complicated than that so
the conversations I want people to
really get a sense of what's happening
in the world because I think a lot of
people could have think about this stuff
but they distract themselves a lot and I
think we really need to sort of build up
a group picture of where things are
going I think my primary aversion to
going out and talking to my neighbors
about the stuff like is just it's it's
the it's just the scope of what needs to
be talked about I don't think I don't
think I can just rob my neighbors and to
like are going out and helping them with
with things that they need help with
yeah that can be a thing but it's the
conversation stuff you know I I feel
like especially
and I think it's a thing that my
generation is stuck with quite a lot is
so I'm trying to reach out to people my
age at the moment so we've got some kind
of like core yeah it's hard a few it's
like the group and the project at the
same time but there's a few things that
were coming up for me that I wanted to
share and see if they'll end which one
was what the Facebook user had suggested
doing something like you have one person
all right ready you have one person
already setting up a barn-raising type
Penn specific fence paintings where my
brain is so not working today
that with a sign there that kind of says
hey do you want to come to help
participate right do you want to come
and work together come and join with a
way for them to join so like an easy
Facebook Facebook group or a website
where people can find out what another
thing is they can suggest what what to
do but for practices that get you to you
want a group that has a practice that
can have like a real culture and then
part of that is doing actual projects
and I don't know if anyone else knows
what a Quaker is I just encountered the
the idea that yesterday I didn't realize
I'm going to actually look into go into
one of their services because what they
do for a service is the adults the kids
go to their own room like like Sunday
school but they are in a room silent
walking around or sitting and when you
feel called to speak you speak and so no
one has a sermon no one had you know you
don't come with something prepared it's
just like as you feel called to speak
you speak and then it goes back to
silence and that sounds like a really
beautiful form of group meditation but
also kind of a way to almost come up
with an idea for what you do together
right you like get people together and
have a brainstorming session with a loud
silent
of like meditation with hey this is what
came up for me and I feel like that
might be the best of both worlds because
they're gonna be like if you're in that
room and someone comes up with an idea
you already feel like you're part of
that idea and are gonna be more likely
to want to to do that and then generate
something for someone else right hey my
grandma needs her friends painted my you
know like having I don't know I don't
know if that's that lens with you yeah
yeah I do like that I did I mean I was
thinking there is probably things
there's often a network already set up
in terms of you know people need help
for this and that and the other so it's
a case of just uncovering it and then
you know finding it had it to become a
part of it so yeah I'm sure we'll find
that as a group yeah and I like I like
the sound of that practice I think that
would be quite an interesting thing to
do and another group yeah yeah I think
just trying a lot of different things
and filling out what makes sense to the
group and keeping things fresh because
really sorry I can take it yeah because
I mean I think the idea is just yeah I
think the idea is just to keep us
talking so that we can process things
because it's hard to just pick a topic
and then work through all of the areas
of their topic touches or to try to
intentionally get the thing that needs
to be expressed out here because people
don't always work in a straightforward
way like that which I'm wondering have
you experimented at all with with
minghao calm
me yeah yeah yeah yeah I've been to a
couple of different meetups yeah I was
originally I was originally gonna start
a meetup around this but I think framing
the group is quite a difficult thing oh
that was the thing you're sending out to
me as well the difficulty with framing
because you want to sort of have the
filter of the people coming in that are
actually on this on the same page as you
but also at the same time have
information about what you're doing
getting out widely enough that it's a
sustainable group um I was going I've
seen some really good ins I'm really bad
we come together on meetup.com and it
does seem could be very much about how
well the purpose of the group is defined
that make difference as to whether it
works or not but yeah if you've seen it
all that was my input yeah my internet
is very leggy so I can't really talk too
much during this cos I interrupt people
that the leg it's even worse but I guess
I'm just looking for more guidance as to
what you want from us Richie like um
what you would like us to focus on
because well does anyone got any
experience doing something so much of us
not like in person but it seems like
there's actually a fair amount of
overlap with this session with the like
trying to create a community of people
whereas it's not an in-person thing like
you know cleaning up a creek or painting
a fence but in this case it's trying to
raise you know project and figure it out
together and what I think I'm hearing
like the the friction is right now with
the de project it sounds like the
project is more about - framework around
the group and like what
the agreed-upon rules and you know how
do we decide who the leader is that sort
of thing rather than the group showing
and doing the thing right whether it's
painting events or cleaning up a creek
it's news like that activity is
partially to give the group of reasons
but then partially also to act as a test
of that framework like if we build a
group you think this framework can they
go out and paint a fence or does it fall
apart because you know two people are
trying to be a leader and so it seems
like it's the question of do you build
the group first and then try to see
where you can you know apply principles
of a framework and like add a single
rule to the group try to emphasize it
try to get buy-in and see how how the
group reacts with felt the group already
being there to build that framework if
that makes sense like you start with the
group and you're the only one trying to
build the framework to start with you
see who is open to it versus trying to
say I only want to build this group
around people who want to put that
framework in or trying to answer
questions about how you build that kind
of a community wish to me it seems super
useful but also hard to explain in a way
that like causes people to go and do
something and join and add in as opposed
to there is an immediate call to action
to a group around hey let's go clean up
that Creek or starting a meetup comm
group off of something like that and
then you're there trying to sort of
answer such questions figure out what
that framework might look like and for
lack of a better term kind of like
trying to take over or have two reasons
for the group to operate at once if that
makes sense
mmm one for the the purpose of the the
activity and then the other one for
trying to figure out what makes this
group work what's the the framework that
we all say hey us all agreeing on these
rules seems to work but if we add this
rule it falls apart hmm yeah I think it
really depends on the character of the
group as as we started so the people
that I'm starting the group with I know
fairly well already right so I think
it'll be a case tapping into their
interests and then how many people I
know
expand its so there's like about five
that are likely to show up and in the
first session they're about 15 who are
you know within the group because I've
started a Facebook or so and you know
I've invited a bunch of people and that
sort of thing but yeah I expect to have
about five or six people in the first
session and then I think it'll just be
yeah I'm trying to I'm trying to trigger
but I think I'm gonna start with the why
like why is it it's feeding any kind of
time trying to build a culture trying to
build a community right and I think I
think like I have the sense that the in
the zeitgeist of at least my generation
and probably probably wider than that
that things are coming undone and you
know I don't want to go to down too far
down the kind of the security rote but I
think there's a positive and a negative
vision that is worth sharing with people
and and then it's like well what do we
want to do about it
given that we are in this scenario where
we could you know let things slip and
things could go really badly or we could
try and work together and try to
reinvigorate a mode of being that is
that is natural to two people working
together as a team having strong bonds
and connections yeah sort of thing but I
think I think yeah I think having
someone because I'm hoping that the
conversation that I that I have with
this this other person is know brings a
parallax to the group because I think
I'm pretty bad at explaining that sort
of stuff because it's so
in scope so hopefully she can help me
refine there before we go into the
physician if you had to pick one thing
what would be the primary goal of yes is
it is it culture building is it
conversations is it sense making is it
doing stuff in the real world what's
though what's the core what's the core
thing
well it's culture building it's it's but
I mean that dead itself is not a
specific thing that's that's pretty
pretty broad those knew what cultural
building might look by kind of thing
that that is that reasonable yeah I
suppose yeah it's just prototyping like
how to actually get something like that
moving and how to actually touch on the
things that I think are really important
so I think philosophy is really
important I think ethics is really
important I think since making is really
important and I just want to find a
quantity in which we can dig into those
things into enough enough dicks so that
we develop them as serious skills it
builds serious connections yeah and it's
kind of that's the primary focus Richie
have you read the micro solidarity stuff
in the game bSpace i I've seen it I'm
not sure if I've read it done oh no I
think I have it's just like a one page
then it's short it's me I believe it's
an entire website I believe the guy's
name is Richard right it's like the
other Richard owes a lot of stuff people
doesn't even have micro solidarity
seriously
come on okay I'll send you to stop after
hmm if you would like yeah that seems to
be like his eye it's been so long since
I've read it was so long been a month
ago
yeah Breen um did he has a framework for
like getting a group of people together
and having them work on a project but
that is part of the the framework is
like how many people I think he says
like seven is ideal and having them work
through resiliency it's more about group
resiliency like um I think from his
sides maybe that's not but I feel like
there's something in there
or for your project as well yeah yeah I
think I think he talks about how you've
got like a single individual then you've
got a group of three into the jewels and
you've got a group of seven and then you
can sort of like it scales up and you've
got different yeah optimal for different
types of things something something to
that effect
yeah yeah I mean I think there's a lot
of stuff out there like this and just I
guess my approach is just to go in there
and try and feel it out as best as
possible I think they just do to my
learning style and there's just so many
nuances that will be you know that's the
particular characteristic of the
individuals you know the the context
yeah and I think you know if if this
initial stab at building that the
culture doesn't work I think it'll mean
trying to find people who are more
specifically interested in this like
we've got a game B group that sitting up
with which could be another 42 staff for
it so it's kind of people who are
already in the know to some extent and I
think it's a lot easier to build
something or to start running as a group
and then finding that momentum because
it really is having that foundational
knowledge that I think is a motivating
factor to keep us showing this kind of
thing
like we wouldn't all be here if we
didn't understand what the facts were
and what the situation is to some extent
so I think yeah it's about finding that
yeah I'm just I'm just testing things I
haven't really done anything like this
before
but it seems really important to me
because you know I think John vivace is
really onto something with its concept
of the religion it's not a religion I
think we need some kind of cultural
bonding framework or frameworks yeah we
am I sent out at least two Adriel I
think I sent it to Kylie as well
probably not Derek but I think we also
talked for an ER major group so maybe
the Brett Weinstein Weinstein talk the
one that you had had sent on the fourth
to call it I had the name rings on the
4th frontier yeah I don't know if you
want to talk about that we can chat
about that and what it was that maybe
resonated with you around this project
in particular yeah so I'm just playing
with this idea at the moment that we
rather than spending our lives just
working I think it would be much much
better for like for people to spend
their lives doing things that are more
meaningful for them more community
orientated like we've just got so much
stuff and we can't really I'm not I'm
not sure if it's entirely true but it
doesn't seem like we can keep increasing
the amount of resources that we're
pulling out of the earth and you know
the throwing environments and things
like that so rather than getting people
to focus on trying to maximize their
with the time in order to pay the bills
and things like that I'm hoping that we
can find ways to cooperate as
communities and enjoy our time and doing
that getting our well worth being from
from those kind of activities so that's
their kind of Highlander frontier
because yeah yeah I mean it's in there
yeah there was a lot in there
he said he condensed like a six month
full time course into an hour the very
end he talks about this engineered
stable abundance that are no turd for us
to to be in the better half of our
genetics we're we're in abundance and
we're kinder to each other rather than
when we are we have scarcity and we show
up a lot less that in order to be able
to have that peace from humanity we need
engineered stable abundance so people
need to feel like they live in an
abundant peaceful world that's taking
care of their needs and it can't be a
lie it has to be something that's
authentically real for them inside and I
think that you're onto something huge
here because it's like the the stuff
you're never gonna have enough of it's
designed so that you it doesn't actually
fill anything it's all about you know
who and it's just accumulation our
planet can't handle that but our planet
can absolutely handle the abundance of
connection and of purpose and doing
stuff and so the more we can tap into
that peace for people even if it's five
people or seven people if they already
have that sense of engineered stable
abundance because they have the
connections then from that space they're
just like a little better off to help
other people who then are a little
better off to help other people and
other people yeah I mean the key is to
find something that's satisfying for
people that's long term sustainable that
isn't yeah just burning throw more and
more resources because the trouble with
mooning through more and more resources
is eventually we're going to create
scarcity for ourselves because we would
have consumed too much of the
environment and then we'll fight other
nations other people ourselves in order
to satisfy the the growth and the
consumption need it's just yes really
I mean potentially the thing is we can
potentially just
you know develop technology that can
just keep going through so we can just
do do this for another two hundred years
or something like that but you know it
seems like if we keep going down the
technology road the economy and the the
kind of the nature of society is just
gonna become more and more brutal
because like we don't have an ethical
framework that we work with them so
nobody there's no authority to say
what's right and what's wrong and it's a
real issue you seems to understand at
the moment we'll you know fifty hundred
years time yeah I feel like we already
know that deep in our deep in ourselves
and that's where a lot of the unrest
comes from individually is that we do
not feel in any way engineered stable
abundance we do not feel even if we have
even if we're what the part of the 1% we
don't feel abundant not that I know and
we don't feel at peace
we don't feel whereas like the idea that
an outside Authority some religion some
government can dictate to you that you
need to act better without giving you
the capacity to be able to act better
like all we actually have to do is have
engineered stable abundance because then
you you just do act better right like
you you can share with your neighbors
and be shared with and have trust that
you're gonna be taking care of you don't
need to hoard resources you don't need
to accumulate things but it can't be
something that is done from on high like
it has to be something that is truly
felt in the individual and to me like
getting a group of people together and
asking them like what would help you
feel more abundance right like right now
on this planet what not would make you
feel at complete perfect abundance and
peace but like what would help you get
that little bit of extra help so that
you are able to give more and be more
and and find those that yeah well I mean
I think straight away it is just
building a community will will be so
satisfying for people just because we
were really disconnected at these days
spending a lot of time on Facebook and
all this kind of stuff so the month the
meaning crisis sort of has rendered a
lot of us dissatisfied and depressed and
all these kinds of things so I think
just trying to restart those connections
and and actually address some of the
more meaningful things will you know the
habit own hopefully boost to people's
felt experience of things and and I
think yeah the personal growth just
going out and doing things and
challenging yourself and and and just
being noticed I think that that's one
thing I'm noticing a lot within people
is just this this need to be to be seen
to be recognized to be valued so giving
people a space to find a niche that they
can occupy and they can beat that person
within a community I think people really
need that because originally the group
was going to be centered around this
idea of tell me your story so I was
gonna go out and start a meetup group
and people are gonna show up and just
tell the story that they needed to tell
because I was noticing a lot of the
people in my life were just they were
just talk and that just tell tell me a
story about you know whatever it was on
was that was on the line and I think
part of that is just people need to
process their experience and part of it
is people need to know that they met it
to other people and but I bet if I
didn't well I talked to a psychologist
about that particular idea and you see
it's probably gonna be pretty risky just
because you'll have people turning up
and they'll be like cuz this kinda no
constrains and people just talk and talk
and talk I mean yeah
can I just a little bit to this notion
of abundance because I mean III agree
with I agree with almost everything Bret
says but I do think there's a little bit
of a danger in that there's implicit in
it is kind of this assumption they're
assuming that abundance can be
engineered that that feeling of
emptiness you know that Hungry Ghost
thing will just go away and I'm not
convinced of that I'm not absolutely
convinced their abundance is also a
place within right I mean yes you can't
it's very very difficult to feel
abundance within when when when you want
in the real world right but abundance is
also a place within right once so I'm
slightly leery of this engineered
abundance being a panacea sort of thing
and I'm not saying you say like that but
I'm saying there's a danger that can be
viewed like that hmm yeah I mean one of
the things that I was thinking about the
other day is just this idea of the need
for objective verification and what I
mean by that is I think no matter how
much you're getting positive
reinforcement from a community I think
there's this need to be like wool like
especially you know if you're a more
kind of dominant as a person or more
competitive you kind of like whoa
and now I just out compete can't really
if you want to explain but if you can if
you can accumulate leverage against
people by doing a particular thing like
starting a business so something like
that people can't argue with that like
folks it works and and you know there's
no question that it does work
[Music]
is this my internet connection or
Ritchie's
he said sort of ups and downs throughout
the gate I'm never sure whether it's me
ya know it's him because well he's been
been freezing like this I've been
watching the other panels and like I can
always see you slightly adjusting here
so it shows that the all the other band
at this time and you put your meters
that are you saying I'm a fidget sir
probably probably not as much as me I
know I'm Owen jingyan this and adjusting
and oh okay and that did not work now
it's frozen is that's just nothing wait
till I see him moving in there and then
if he comes back and he's a 15-6 person
well we'll see
but as to what you said Eric about the
abundance I agree that like if all we
have is resource abundance which is both
one of the most difficult things to
obtain and it doesn't deal with those
with the shadow it doesn't deal with but
not sufficient right is the phrase that
comes to mind and necessary most yeah
just why and yet like if we stick with
the other form of abundance which is
like the internal abundance the
abundance of connection and community
the abundance of like you are seen and
and respected is the wrong word word
your seed is worthy for exactly who you
are as much as we can do that in small
groups then there's already that sense
of via the abundance that does get you
there the abundance that is eternal
peace that helps you you grow and that's
available now that's not something we
need to wait till game before starts in
here right with although all of it
starts in here yeah yeah absolutely and
it is for an individual I mean I've
reached there mostly for myself but
there's a big piece that it's hard to
get there by yourself it's hard to see
yourself as worthy without other people
seeing you is worthy yeah yeah and still
the best thing we can do for other
people once we've went through that
show is to see them and love them where
they are so that they don't have to do
that journey alone and be lonely they
already get that sense
of abundance like you don't need to love
you will love you until you can kind of
thing as whatever is that sounds I mean
another part of abundance is rather than
having more is needing less right so
that that that's being content with less
is also a pathway towards abundance
right absolutely
it's a pretty important pathway but like
just like the abundance like if everyone
around you has a car and everyone around
you as a house everyone gets going
there's that sense of you're lacking
right whereas if everyone else is
starving and you have food on your table
you're gonna feel like you have more
more abundance than they do but that
isn't true abundance like that like it
can't be compared to other people
it has to be I'm abundant because I have
this not because other people don't know
because I have more or less than someone
else just I have it and they can to its
III in fact I even a lack of want is
even a better word than abundance right
because it's not about loads of stuff
it's just about an absence of fear and
absence of fear of wanting you know what
I mean it's that it's that yes we've
come up again playing we're done well I
think the I think is biological reasons
why we have this kind of what they've
got this I should I should have that as
well but there's also like if you come
to an equilibrium then you've also got
this well I feel like I'm better than
people so I'm gonna I'm gonna try and
prove that I am better than people and
then it's like there's the step to set
dissatisfaction against mediocrity that
so so we've got kind of these two
conflicting drives within a collective
psyches which I think are going to be
really difficult to mediate because
we're going to still need to find ways
to compete against one another
the thing is we need to figure out
outlets for these natural impulses that
don't lead to going falling back into
game theory that's kind of well I think
that's going to be a really difficult
exactly what sport this for yeah
you that right sports and games that's
exactly what they're for hmm for me the
analogy is in the Olympics the Olympics
has one gold medal winner and everyone
else is a loser if you are there in your
sport to only get the gold medal chances
are you're not gonna be happy
whereas if you're there to compete at
your best level including you're
competing against people right you're
not there to get nothing but you're
there to get like there's a difference
between the internal competition of like
me trying to be my best and if you're
seeking it from the outside even if you
win the gold medal but you didn't show
up and do your best you should actually
feel shitty if you showed up and did
your best and gave it your all and you
didn't even get bronze you should feel
good it's not necessary like shouldn't
matter what it does but though there's
one there's one crucial thing right if
you turn up every day try your hardest
and all you're doing is to try and beat
your time against the clock right and
you turn up every day you train as hard
as you can just to try and improve your
time improve your time improve your time
you are not gonna get as good as you
would if you raced against people yeah
you know that that visceral competition
in the moment against another human
being you know what I mean there is no
substitute for that for that for the
driving forward it can be you know what
I mean it's its harnessing that taking
the destructive war you know win-lose
thing out of it that's that's that's the
key but yeah you can never drive
yourself as hard as other people in
competition against you can drive you it
also gets hard when you're talking about
if you're trying to compete in something
that you're good at there's all these
different sports like I don't want to
compete in basketball oh I think maybe I
can do long distance running I'll try
that but then you get you know people
like Jeff Bezos and they're like well
I'm not good that but I can do
good at this sort of you know hiring a
lot of wealth and running a business in
a certain way and doing some with that
we're now that gives him a stage to
compete on the world stage that's his
Olympics and if there is no outlet then
what do you dislike if Jeff paid you
know if you know if the next Jeff Bezos
looks at all the sports in the Olympics
is this man I don't want to do any of
those looks at something that he can do
that maybe I want to create a grab you
name just me and see the game that is
there but that competing in it is
damaging I think that's where you you
ever read like it's sort of figuring out
right like there might be there's a
sport of target shooting but maybe we're
saying hey maybe we don't want the sport
where we're shooting at people we're
gonna agree that that one's off the
table because that's something else
entirely and it's talking about where
we're agreeing that it's okay to compete
here and it and these other areas where
were like no because in order to get to
the top and to have that you know if
you're competing against someone it
helps you grow and it was like that the
picture that they took a couple of
months ago of the person who ran the
first it was the first under two hour
marathon or salute or something that
there was some world record that was
broken but if you look at the picture
there's like six people right behind me
yeah all competing together it's moving
that for everyone which when you get
into certain sport right like extreme
capitalism you get into okay but
everyone competing this and moving this
up and up and and raising that bar is
incredibly damaging everywhere else and
identify that how do we say that's how
sport that one's too dangerous you have
ten minutes left for this session
Richie's or anything else you want us to
concentrate on are you good with just
having a good the thing that said of
coming up to me here ISM is around
feedback so that's how I understood like
that engineered abundance to be it's
like giving the feedback at that right
level
which means that you've got a sense of
having enough but also not pushing past
that limit and I think that it might be
a bit the same with with everything you
know like in terms of whether you're
just trying to compete with you as
powerful or trying to compete Atlas you
know out with other people in the
Olympics or whatever the case may be
it's like it's always about like getting
the feedback as to as to fitness you
know like as to how appropriate
something is within a certain
circumstance actually wondering if in
some ways this this almost applies for
what which is looking at doing as well
is to kind of go you know what is it
that we can go and do as a group that
then gives us the feedback to know
whether this is something that's healthy
to have within our cultural setting you
know unhealthy so it's almost like going
and trying something and then reflecting
on it and doing each other you know the
feedback to kind of go okay so is this
making us all feel more abundant or that
making it feel like we're missing out on
things that we're feeling like it's fair
are we feeling like it's ethical is it
you know to try to get some of those and
almost like feedback loop controls but
using that you know the cultural
mechanism to to shape it anyway yeah
yeah cuz there's a bunch of things that
I'm so wisdom is something I'm really
focused on like I think wisdom is a
great way to more accurately focus a
group of people so if somebody is like
ah you know I'm winning all of these
things I should be getting a bigger
share of the pie than anyone else that's
potentially persuasive if you don't have
the foresight to see where that leads
and communication is another really
important one how can we effectively
communicate with one another our points
of view and really come to a decision
about you know how we structure
ourselves and just metabolizing some of
those potentially dangerous aspects
about
it's nowadays like yeah it's because
yeah it seems like because of mode
because most of history we've sort of
always been in this crunch time we've
been always like we haven't really had
the time to deliberate these things so I
think now while times are so good I
think we need to try and focus and hone
that their interpersonal communication
the wisdom the the the metabolizing of
social dynamics because I just don't
think we've done very well up there at
the moment phrase metabolizing social
dynamics I like that phrase very much
hmm yeah and I think I think that's
that's that really yet because a lot of
it is you know people just don't have
the space to help to express things in a
healthy way you know we've got a lot of
drug addiction we've got just yeah I
mean there's just so much awful stuff in
the world and I think a lot of that is
just misplaced emotional energy because
yeah I mean the the the way that we
treat animals in the farming industry is
just so horrific and I think you need
anyone who really looks at it you'd be
like what the are we doing
you saw chickens you should come eat
much okay just kind of are very very
nice hens who do not know their place
and we should absolutely have a game be
Airbnb can be every day that's too many
bees go and visit each other everyone
put their places up that's a brilliant
idea came game no air game B or
something something
I'm like in your circles like ya know
would be totally couch surfing and it
could just be that discount surfing but
also no air gain B is a brilliant work
is a brilliant name because that's what
you do you get to air game B when you go
you just shoot the about you know
your air in game it's brilliant it's but
it's a brilliant idea you could actually
if you wanted to make money out of this
but it's a brilliant idea cash
in while they're making t-shirts of game
B yeah while they're doing game beat
caching caching while you can more than
make the tribe before it dies cash in
while you can but seems very gaming as
cheap as possible sell them for his
money so did you see them
hi Billy they cropped up a few days ago
it made me laugh I think it did make me
chuckle it did make me chuckle that's
really funny
yes og yeah yeah so business is actually
a thing that the group could potentially
do and then yeah I guess I guess the
trick is like finding a way to do that
that's fits with the ethical kind of
framework that we work in because I
would like to become like I think the
goal of becoming a self-contained unit
that self-sustained through so you know
some kind of cuz cuz yeah one of the
questions that goes round is like well
how do we how do we support ourselves
going into the transition of game came
bit how do we move away from game a and
I think one way to do that is just to
form groups of people who have the same
ethics and try to make money in a way
that is the most aligned with you know
because because the thing is we all have
to go to make money anyway so
for the meantime we might as well work
together build that into relational
skills and you know try and construct
something together and in creating a
work environment where we can you know
support each other and and you know I
mean getting money involved always
introduces new problems but can we solve
those problems I don't know yeah you
know what some of some of what I would
love to see you know in a local area see
I don't know how long I'm staying here
I'm just moved to Sydney I might only be
here for a year so I'm you know
reluctant to put down roots but would be
this this thing there's always there's
like maker spaces and there's you know
in places that sort of focus on you know
upcycling and there's you know to
libraries and things like that and they
always seem to be done as these separate
pieces that it would be very interesting
because it has like network we've been
going on you know within a community for
anything that's to do you know Jane B
ish you know like even if it's like a
couple of steps away just sort of have
you know coming together and actually
working together there have been loads
of attempts to do this Kylie over the
years
loads of attempts to create like
umbrella organizations under which all
of these activist groups can get
together because they're all on the same
team you know there's been lots and lots
of incarnations of attempts to do this
it's it's it's so important it's so
important it has to happen no one has
yet succeeded do let me know if you
figure out to do it well the main thing
I'm thinking is that you know like you
need a few people probably a group
around the size of what rich is talking
about there say a dozen people who are
actually members of at least you know
say that there's ten in total that you
identify that each person is like a
member of say four of them mmm I mean
because it starts to stitch poor
relationships together I don't think I
would quite a go for an umbrella
organization I don't think that can work
I think it's the kind of thing where
people are always going to focus on the
things that are of most interest to them
it's exactly what happens every time
I mean I wonder if instead of an
umbrella organization it just becomes
sort of like you know game be version of
Meetup where there's a network of people
that have all sort of set them
interested NIST's sometimes I might be
online sometimes it may be in your area
if you go traveling or you move you may
still want to you know access that same
network but then it there's like that
framework that Richie's talking about
Brett's not as like free form as meetup
where it's here's the group go do
whatever you want for whatever reason
you just keep paying us your your meetup
comm group fee and other than that we
don't care it's like it's the framework
for whether it's an online group or an
in-person and whether that in-person is
a business you're trying to clean up
creaks what's common between trying to
keep that group together how do you
account for different people for
different values and then trying to
build that so that whatever group it is
you're saying okay here's the framework
that we said that's worked for all these
other groups part of it isn't just each
group it's to keep building that
framework and without the geographic
proximity of a group of people you know
that having a group people you can
actually be in the same room with or get
together with in a bar somewhere locally
do you not I mean that kind of thing it
makes it extremely difficult I mean to
actually do anything in the real world
you know what I mean it just ends up
becoming discussion groups and then when
I say just discussion don't get me wrong
they're the most beautiful things in the
world but you know that but but but in
terms of you know taking action in the
world there and so maybe maybe just
accept that that's what you're doing is
you're forming discussion groups making
friends forming relationships and who
knows what's going to come of those down
the road kind of thing but without the
geographical proximity I do I do think
the the the bit of you know the the part
of your loop of agreeing on a thing that
you're gonna do in the world going out
and doing that right and that being part
of the process I see that being
extremely difficult in an online
community unless unless you unless
something occurred to me before that you
goes right back to I was saying at the
very very start of the conversation to
but maybe you could make a commitment
within the group each week or each month
or whatever month might be better that
during the course of the next month
I am going
to involve five people in my
neighborhood in something I don't know
what it is yet I don't know where easier
but that's my undertaking is to vote
involve five people in my immediate
proximity right in a thing that we can
all do together whatever it might be
when you get back to tell you stories
about what you did what you tried what
went well what went badly have a laugh
about it you know to me and then you
build the community around the stories
of the things that you're doing and and
that kind that that sounds to me like it
could be really nice mm-hmm
totally and I think this is on all local
meetups right we're like if you come on
I mean it is it's an online group but
the whole point is to meet up locally so
you're organized into like here's my
city and then you see the different
meetup groups and you can join them and
go out and attend you have the similar
thing but instead of just being a random
group of people because Viacom is very
random it is that like the specific
purpose that like the the the culture
creator type group or the whole point
it's not the groups are a big part of it
because that's how it sort of
materializes in the world and I think
that's also where you get a lot of your
members from it's sort of two different
parallel lines you have your group you
know your groups as they throw up in the
world where they're going out and doing
things you'll have people saying you
know they walk by and see ten people
painting a fence
oh what a guy's doing oh we're going and
painting fences in the neighborhood or
cleaning up a creek or whatever you'll
have people who just want to join that
and if you have five people show up and
there's this this layer of here's how
we're operating and why and oh we had a
meeting and and decided to try this new
way to operate so we're gonna try it out
you hear that and the people who are
interested might be like wait wait what
I guess talking about and that's where
you get the people joining the higher
the higher level group if you just want
to paint fences just your up and paint
fences and you've got groups within
groups then as well right because on one
end you're doing a local meetup group to
do the thing that you've been talking
about in your online group right so yeah
and then so yeah you can't with an idea
now something you're gonna do locally
you organize a local meetup group about
that you do that thing and then once a
week or once a fortnight whatever you
get together with your own
and talk about the thing that you're
doing there and maybe you can
personalize a little bit between porn
wenona me it's a beautiful thing this
has got real potential it's a beautiful
thing
Thanks so I think one of the biggest
things is its ability to like if you
don't care about that upper level
completely ignore it just show up and be
with people in your community you might
like not actually know what exists and
that's fine there's going up and doing
it and working in the community and in
my mind that that also makes the
framework stronger if not everyone
involved in the group has full buy on
every tenet but they are still like the
group can still handle that person and
you can hand all the different people
coming up you have your different rules
how to handle the different situations
it becomes a way more flexible robust
thing that can then you know set the
framework for more and more but it's
able to handle people that don't care
and you know we'll try to break the
rules and might not know what's yeah but
like that constant reinforcement what do
you think of all this rich this is your
thing I mean Rajon I've got a bit
carried away here this is your thing
though what do you think of all this
yeah yeah yeah it's it's good yeah I
just find letting people find how they
want to participate although I do like
one of the things that I would like to
see is that we we come to some kind of
agreement as a species on some basic
things because I think well I think we
really need to build a solid ground
philosophically that we all share
to some extent because I think it's
necessary in order to like solve
agreement we you can you can still bring
your religion and whatever your religion
is but this is just like and just a
shared space that we all agree with it's
like okay these are the things that we
boldly aiming to be lovely a very and
then you have your own what
I think it's very tricky for any any
anything that everyone can agree on is a
very very very tricky thing I think the
best you can hope for is that within the
groups that form broad agreement on
those axioms kind of thing but then
there are other groups that have
completely different axioms but there is
sufficient cross-pollination you know
between these groups that some
communication even though it may not be
head-on but some communication actually
is going on between them the other
porous boundaries between them at the
individual level at the small group
level so yeah yeah I think we need to
unwind rival resin if we don't hit my
Cantonese Laurie say I was just thinking
of something that I'm pretty sure that
Eric brought up in the different
conversation that we had a while back
about the difference between was it
values and strategy I know the example
that used Eric is about yes nonviolent
communication yeah yeah yeah have this
you know two villagers are on the side
of a river and then what we end up
arguing about is actually the strategy
of how do that you can agree on those
basic needs and I think if we're going
to find some kind of an ethical thing
that everybody can agree with it's going
to be that thing it's going to be needs
based it's going to you know what it's
actual nature of the human by Kennedy's
that's right you know we all breathe the
same air we all want we all love our
children you know I mean it's that it's
that yeah yeah yeah absolutely yeah and
then trying to get more involved than
that I don't think I don't think that's
ever going to work but we have to find a
way to I think up regulate those things
that we can really you know fairly
easily agree that we actually have in
common
as to people like famous matters to
everybody like what famous is so hey
they're like everyone kiss agree on that
but you know we'll probably greatly want
some kind of famous we don't have that
but I think it's you know I actually
don't think it's very far away I think
we it's already there it's just that we
need to yeah there's a certain we need
upregulation okay and thank you much ya
know that where it's though kind of the
wording about what you agree on so if
you're talking about paradise is the
rule or the thing that we're going on
how that takes shape and what that looks
like
or is it just that statement of like no
she a fan is line every everything goes
to warm that will try different tactics
but the thing is that okay parents is
important we wait things to be right
that's the need we really need things to
be fair we can argue about how we do
that all working towards those few core
tenets of like if it's not towards this
we can have a conversation on okay maybe
when isn't Paris important it sounds
like it always is maybe a couple but Bob
a lot that we all agree on okay
and these situations you know maybe
security is more important but the
overall framework of just that really
loose statement of like fairness is
important we all agree on that
great we maybe make it like a little bit
more precise if you have still agree no
okay then we'll just keep it there
that's a--that's a real problem as soon
as you start to get precise about what
do you mean by fair then you're into
robots and arguments and Wars and but
the thing we can all agree on is we want
things to be fair right but so in the
Brett Weinstein talk that some of most
of us listen to he talks about hating
utopians not like he knew topi ins and
his main argument which I am a hundred
percent for is that when you maximize
for one trait it costs everything else
because of diminishing returns and so we
can all agree that we love that fairness
connection needs met all of those things
because there are different orders for
us we don't agree on how much you need
to do right
because there's always the diminishing
return if we can actually figure out the
diminishing return then that's the point
like it's like right so fairness even if
my highest order is fairness I can't
have every every resource going to
fairness because it costs everything
else a society and so finding the point
of diminishing returns and we're really
bad at that in society like parenting I
just wrote this tweet of like parents
you run like I think I figured out the
diminishing returns fun parenting I look
like a crap parent because I'm not
willing to put in every last second of
my time and energy into my kid because
quite frankly that would hurt her more
than it would help her and it would
definitely hurt me more than it would
help me and it's like finding but but
like as a parent I'm supposed to write
like every last ounce of every energy
every dollar should be going to her and
it's like no it's sort of like a
universal principle of sorry Adriel go
ahead I think we may have been sort of
saying the same thing in different ways
take the pret Oh principal right where
it's like 20 percent of the in the case
of pret oh the peas generate 80% of the
stuff where it's like you identified
that and you say that's the most
important thing not if we're saying that
fairness is important you find your
diminishing return you find that initial
part where 20 percent of the work yes
you're 80 percent of the way there and
you try to do that across the board you
identify all these different things
we're okay fairness is important we
could theoretically organize a society
around that entirely cuz we're thing is
important but other things are also
important so we identify each of those
things find out where you know the
principle that you that universal thing
happens we're okay here is where the
diminishing return happens for all these
things and try to hit that same level
across the board the freighter abundance
the abundance peace of like I'm sorry no
principle and that when you feel you
have abundance you act from a better
place but part of it is you don't feel
you have an abundance because of the
Pareto principle right you're like I'm
doing 80 percent on the twenty percent
it's like yeah here but somebody else is
doing
somewhere what is your abundance right
what do I need can I own that I feel
abundant what do I need to feel more
abundant without needing it to be geared
to what society has because that doesn't
actually bring you abundance right
having the car your neighbor has you
might think it does then you have it if
like everyone has cars it's not helping
you feel superior you actually need it /
wanted I'm like having the interpersonal
abundance like do I feel abundant with
this diminishing return in society of
like where do i where where's my Prater
principle right like where do I give and
feel good about it maybe I'm never gonna
be the 20% anywhere but I'm you know the
next the 5% next to it so many places
right it's like cool or not if you're
the lowest and everywhere but you're
there with a lot of this our ability to
measure it is gonna be suspect at best
so we're not gonna hit that exactly 20%
I think if we're using the proto
principle as an example it's say okay if
we were to be as efficient as possible
let's say we take the top 25% of the
yield and harvest it that means the last
25% we're gonna see them on the ground
saying why aren't we picking that it's
right there you like to cut there's only
one P in each of them and it's just not
worth it and it's sort of being able to
identify it and saying okay if fairness
is super-important here's our biggest
returns here's the things that we can do
easily to get the best return here's
sort of where the cut off happens here's
all of these things that as far as we
know aren't worth it right like it takes
so much to implement and we'll only get
that much back if we learn new
information where maybe that change is
great we can reassess it but it's
figuring out and sort of identifying
where the diminishing returns are yeah
sort of agreeing on yet in an ideal
world we could do everything that
implemented fairness but we're saying
these you know kenner or 20 things we're
not sure how that would work
so right now we're all agreeing to not
do that thing and that's the you know if
75% of the peas that are left on artists
ed which looks really bad if you're the
gardener you're like why didn't you
there's still so much left to do yeah
that's intentional I'm doing other stuff
doing that that's that's when he
represent in every field I think
I'd love to see is a bunch of all that
all the different things that are sort
of like fairness you know it's like we
all agree on fairness and more agreed
that just important then you know what
we kind of had a list or say ten things
I like a list that Ritchie started in
the document that listed like you know
the the no driver is a non-violent and
and those things starting that kind of a
list where you might be able to start to
dissect them and group them and stuff
but yeah actually being able to list
them out and saying here's it do we all
agree who disagrees and why you know
what's the order but they're all
understand that like even if fairness is
your top priority right we're never
gonna get to the hundred of those
fairness 100 percent agreement that's a
really really really good point and no
absolutely works on agreement as well
right what if you can get eighty percent
of people behind it's a no idea pretty
easily because it's obviously good then
you don't need to fight tooth and now
for the other 20 percent
there's better ways to invest your time
those people who are in their net last
twenty percent hopefully they're in the
eighty percent in a bunch of other areas
where they exactly that's the important
things to remember that was really that
was brilliant Jubilee that was for me
anyway that was super insightful that
was brilliant I think we just solved
game B let's say I think we can do more
here we just did it to Kayla I was
actually just one I was actually just
thinking that you know that so once
you've got all of those maybe instead of
us trying to argue about which is most
important to instead be able to focus on
which ones we we feel are not being met
for us at the moment
so you know it's well you basically only
looking to repair something rather than
come up with some kind of abstract
statement about yeah yeah
locking yourself into some kind of
definition and then if you you know if
you if you're doing this with a group of
say twenty people who are all going
around
saying I feel like it's not fair it's
not fair it's not fair it's not fair
then kind of go okay so in it's a little
trying to find a way to make this more
fair right so no perfectly fair but you
know like less unfair more fair and just
kind of have this sort of picture of
like when things are out of balance
right and that is the thing that we're
sort of aiming towards rather than
trying to you know prioritize all the
time based on some sort of tax ideal
anyway all right well we're like 15
minutes almost gone
who sixty minutes over at the moment
this is we usually just stop and then we
just have this conversation without
recording it I'm glad we were still
recording yeah but would anyone like to
give any closing statements before we
say goodbye to Facebook and YouTube just
thanks for spending the time to check
with me I know I'm super vague but I'm
figuring it out it's gonna be an out in
the field kind of thing but this was
this was these will chair now like the
ideas I think we the last 15 minutes was
the best 15 minutes oh absolutely
absolutely and for anyone watching take
this home take this home tell your
parents yeah identify the point of
diminishing returns on everything all
right goodbye see you next week next
week we're meeting at the same time at
what was 2:00 p.m. our time so an hour
and 20 minutes ago from right this
second the one personal gym and we're
gonna be doing a solution raising which
one we don't know yet health care or
food it looks like by the two people who
answered the survey all right back back
Joe